<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The excellency of the Christian revelation, as it promiseth assistance, and compleat salvation to sinners a sermon preach'd in the Cathedral Church of St. Paul, November the 6th, 1699, being the eighth, for this year, of the lecture founded by the Honourable Robert Boyle, Esq. / by Samuel Bradford ...</title>
            <author>Bradford, Samuel, 1652-1731.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29101</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4111</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19744</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12115792</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12115792</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54296</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29101)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54296)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 759:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The excellency of the Christian revelation, as it promiseth assistance, and compleat salvation to sinners a sermon preach'd in the Cathedral Church of St. Paul, November the 6th, 1699, being the eighth, for this year, of the lecture founded by the Honourable Robert Boyle, Esq. / by Samuel Bradford ...</title>
                  <author>Bradford, Samuel, 1652-1731.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Timothy, 1st, I, 15 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Salvation --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54296:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Excellency of the Chriſtian Revelation, as it promiſeth Aſſiſtance, and compleat Salvation to Sinners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd in the Cathedral Church of St. <hi>PA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>L, November</hi> the 6th. 1699.</p>
            <p>Being the Eighth, for this Year, of the Lecture founded by the Honourable <hi>Robert Boyle,</hi> Eſq;</p>
            <p>By <hi>SAM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EL BRADFORD,</hi> Rector of St. <hi>Mary le Bow,</hi> Chaplain in Ordinary to His Majeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers Chappel,</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:54296:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54296:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 TIM 1.15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>This is a faithful ſaying, and worthy of all acceptation, that Chriſt Jeſus came into the World, to ſave Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.—</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN diſcourſing of the Method, in which the great <hi>Mediator between God and Man, Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> hath undertaken <hi>to ſave Sinners,</hi> I propos'd to conſider the <hi>Neceſſities</hi> of fallen Men, and thereby to evince both that we had very great need of the aſſiſtance of a <hi>Mediator,</hi> and that no Method, which we can poſſibly think of, could have ſo fully anſwer'd the end of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding for our <hi>Neceſſities,</hi> as that which our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour, by his <hi>coming into the World</hi> hath been pleas'd to take.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Neceſſities</hi> of Men I reduc'd to <hi>four</hi> Heads.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> A ſuſpicion and jealouſy of Mind concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, and an Alienation from him, as conſequent thereupon.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> A groſs ignorance of God, of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and of the ſeveral particulars of their Duty.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> An indiſpoſition and inability to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with the Divine Will, although it ſhould be fully and clearly reveal'd.</item>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:54296:3"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> After all, an incapacity of removing thoſe other evil and miſchievous Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to which their ſins had expos'd them, and of obtaining for themſelves that compleat Salvation, which they ſtood in need of.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The <hi>two</hi> former of theſe I have conſider'd at large, and now proceed to thoſe <hi>two</hi> which remain, which I ſhall treat of with greater Brevity, what I have to offer upon theſe Heads, not requiring ſo much inlargment, as on the former.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly</hi> therefore, The next Difficulty which fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en Men are under, is this, That they find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves indiſpos'd and unable to comply with the Divine Will, even when it is fully and clearly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to them.</p>
            <p>Whoſoever will impartially conſider what I have offer'd, touching the <hi>Precepts</hi> and <hi>Example</hi> of our Bleſſed Saviour, and will ſeriouſly ſtudy the Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the New Teſtament, in which a particular account of each of them is contain'd, muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that a profeſs'd Chriſtian cannot want ſufficient <hi>Inſtruction,</hi> in all the particulars of his Duty: But there is ſtill ſomething farther neceſſary, <hi>viz.</hi> to be both <hi>able</hi> and <hi>willing</hi> to comply with the <hi>Precepts,</hi> and to imitate the <hi>Example</hi> thus ſet before him. Chriſtians themſelves confeſs, and complain with the Apoſtle,
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.23.</note> that they <hi>ſee another Law in their Members, warring againſt the Law of their Minds,</hi> which, antecedently to the Grace of the Goſpel, <hi>brings them into Captivity.</hi> And the Adverſaries of Chriſtianity make this a great Objection againſt our holy Profeſſion, and I doubt not but that it is, at the bottom, the principal ground of their Infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:54296:3"/>that the <hi>Precepts</hi> of our Lord are too ſtrict, and his <hi>Example</hi> too exact, to be complyed with and imitated by humane Nature. And this is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently the Reaſon, why ſo many profeſs'd Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians act diſagreeably to their Profeſſion, <hi>viz.</hi> That their Appetites and Paſſions are too ſtrong for their Underſtanding and Reaſon: they know the Will of God, and inwardly approve it, but cannot prevail with themſelves to obey it: <hi>to Will,</hi> that is to have ſome faint and imperfect inclination to act according to the conviction of their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>is preſent with them;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 18, 19.</note> but how <hi>to perform that which is good, they find not:</hi> So that <hi>the good which they would, they do not; but the evil which they would not, that they do,</hi> as the ſame Apoſtle emphatically expreſſes it. And all this is but one of thoſe evil Conſequences, which, as I obſerved in a former Lecture,
<note place="margin">Lect. ij. p. 20. 21.</note> naturally follow our apoſtacy from God.</p>
            <p>My preſent Buſineſs therefore is to ſhew, what Proviſion our <hi>Mediator</hi> hath made in this caſe; and this I ſhall do, in the <hi>three</hi> following Particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Our Bleſſed Saviour hath provided in this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, by annexing ſuch Sanctions to his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, as do naturally tend moſt powerfully to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence our Minds.</p>
            <p n="2">II. By promiſing the aſſiſtance of the Divine Spirit, for the enabling us to do what of our ſelves we cannot.</p>
            <p n="3">III. By ſettling ſuch inſtitutions to be conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerv'd and us'd in his Church, as are both in their own Nature proper to excite us, and are moreover deſign'd as Means of conveying the Grace of the Holy Spirit to us.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:54296:4"/> I. By annexing ſuch Sanctions to his Precepts, as do naturally tend moſt powerfully to influence our Minds.</p>
            <p>The Precepts of Chriſtianity are all of them ſo perfectly good in their own Nature, and ſo tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly agreeable to the Underſtanding of a reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Creature, that every Man to whom they are made known, would readily comply with them, if it were not for the ſeeming Pleaſures of Sin, and the difficulties with which ſome inſtances of Virtue ſeem to be attended; <hi>ſeem,</hi> I ſay; for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all, the Experience of every good Chriſtian fully ſatisfies him, that the preſent Pleaſure, which attends a faithful compliance with the Precepts of the Goſpel, greatly preponderates all its dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties; as the uneaſineſs and the remorſe, which attend a ſinful Courſe of Life, do on the other hand render its Pleaſures very incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable.
<note place="margin">Prov. 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>The ways of Wiſdom are ways of Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantneſs, and all her Paths are Peace;</hi> and to him that is become a thorow Chriſtian, <hi>the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God are not Grievons.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 John 5.3.</note> But nevertheleſs, thus it falls out, through the Error and Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Mankind, that Men are frequently miſled by a preſent Pleaſure, which they feel in comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with their ſenſual inclinations; and that the practice of Chriſtian Piety and Virtue, foraſmuch as it thwarts ſuch inclinations, becomes difficult and irkſome to them. Now to balance this, our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour hath by his Goſpel propos'd, over and above the preſent ſatisfaction and Pleaſure which are to be found in compliance with his Laws, future rewards for our Obedience, and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Puniſhments for our Diſobedience.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:54296:4"/>
            <p> The Paſſions of Hope and Fear were implanted in our Nature by him who made us, to be a check upon our preſent Senſe; and they are of eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Uſe to us, during this ſtate of our Tryal, to preſerve us from being influenc'd by the falſe and deceitful appearances of preſent and ſenſible Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. And although we cannot be ſaid to have ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived at a Chriſtian Frame and Conſtitution of Spirit, till we heartily approve the Precepts of our Religion, and chuſe to comply with them, on account of their own intrinſick reaſonableneſs and goodneſs; yet 'tis uſually by the hope of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and the fear of Puniſhments, that our Minds are at firſt awaken'd, and our thoughts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come duly fix'd; and even after we have attain'd to a ſincere and prevalent love of Piety and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue upon their own account, yet ſtill our hopes and fears are of great uſe to us, to excite our Minds, to quicken our Endeavours, and to turn the Scale, upon all Emergencies, againſt the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of Senſe.</p>
            <p>And by how much the more conſiderable the Objects of our hope and fear are, by ſo much the greater is the influence which they will have up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us. For which reaſon, the Goſpel hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to us <hi>ſuch</hi> Rewards and Puniſhments in the life to come, as to thoſe who thoroughly believe and conſider them, will appear infinitely to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weigh all the preſent Pleaſures by which fooliſh Sinners are courted, and the preſent difficulties by which they are apt to be diſcouraged. For it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth on the one hand, all that Happineſs, which humane Nature compleated by the union of a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified Soul with an incorruptible Body, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54296:5"/>to the favor of Almighty God, is capable of; and on the other hand, it threatens all that Miſery, that Men compos'd of Soul and Body reunited, but unregenerated, and abandon'd by God, are obnoxious to; the particulars of which ſtates are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuch as we cannot have a full conception of in this Life; but from the general view which the Goſpel hath given us, both of the <hi>Quality,</hi> and the <hi>Duration</hi> of this future Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Miſery, we have all the reaſon in the World to infer, that nothing, but either down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right disbelief of theſe things, or the want of repreſenting them duly to our Minds, by frequent and ſerious conſideration, can render them inef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual to excite our hope and fear to that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, as will ſerve to influence our tempers and our lives.</p>
            <p>For the farther promoting of which ends, the Goſpel hath fully and clearly aſſerted the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality and Certainty of theſe future Recompences, not ſpeaking of them, as of what may <hi>poſſibly</hi> be, or what is only <hi>probable;</hi> but as of what we may as ſurely depend upon, as upon any other Truths which it hath reveal'd to us, leaving no room for any profeſs'd Chriſtian to doubt or heſitate concerning them.</p>
            <p>And herein it muſt be granted, that the Method taken by the Chriſtian Inſtitution, for exciting our hope and fear, and by conſequence for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us effectually to comply with its Precepts, altogether ſurpaſſes what has been done by any other inſtitution of Religion. It would be ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous to compare the dreams of Pagan Poets, or the Mahometan Fables, concerning the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:54296:5"/>and Puniſhments of the life to come, with the Promiſes and Threatnings of the Goſpel. As to the <hi>Moſaical</hi> Inſtitution, which we Chriſtians acknowledge to have been Divine, it look'd no farther in its Promiſes and Threatnings, at leaſt not in plain and expreſs terms, than to the good and evil things of the preſent life. Not but that wiſe and good Men amongſt the Jews, looking beyond the Letter of their Law, did ſee, tho' obſcurely, into the other World.</p>
            <p>The notion of the Soul's Immortality was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed from Nature and Reaſon, generally em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brac'd by the conſidering part of Mankind: but yet the wiſeſt and beſt Philoſophers expreſs'd themſelves very dubiouſly with reſpect to a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture State, of which ſufficient Evidence might be produc'd both from <hi>Socrates</hi> amongſt the <hi>Greeks,</hi> and <hi>Tully</hi> amongſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> who ſeem to have gone as far as any others in the Expectation and Hope of Immortality; but yet could not ſay enough powerfully to excite the hopes of good Men, or the fears of the Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to ſuch a degree, as might ſuffice to balance the Temptations of the preſent Life, at leaſt with the vulgar and unthinking part of Men, which is by far the greater number. Whereas the Goſpel ſpeaks ſo plainly, and ſo poſitive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of theſe matters, as may be ſufficient to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence all ſorts of Men by whom it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved.</p>
            <p>To conclude this Particular; The belief of the Recompences of the Life to come, as reveal'd by the Goſpel, is that which has made ſo wide a difference between the Chriſtian and the Pagan
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54296:6"/>World. What the State of the Heathen was, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the publiſhing of Chriſtianity, I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd in a former Lecture.
<note place="margin">Lect. ij. p. 23.</note> Men were almoſt univerſally and totally fallen from the <hi>Divine,</hi> and ſunk into the <hi>Animal</hi> Life, eſtranged from God, and enſlav'd by the Devil and their own Luſts: But when the Goſpel was Publiſhed, it awaken'd their Minds, cauſing them to look forward towards another Life, and to conſider the conſequences of their preſent behaviour.</p>
            <p>There are indeed in this degenerate State of the Chriſtian Church, abundance of Men pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing themſelves Chriſtians, who are yet as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reform'd as the worſt of Infidels: But then, 'tis becauſe they do not heartily believe, or at leaſt do not at all conſider the Principles of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity. But as this is certain, that where Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity is Profeſs'd, there are far greater num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of all Ranks of Men, who are perſuaded to the practice of Piety and Virtue, than there are in other parts of the World; ſo 'tis as evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that this is in great meaſure owing to the Principles which I am now ſpeaking of. 'Tis the belief of a future Life, which keeps bad Men in the Chriſtian World, from being much worſe than they are: 'Tis that which firſt awak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened and excited moſt of thoſe, who are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed from an evil Courſe: And 'tis that, which thoſe who are become Chriſtians in good ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, hearty lovers of Piety and Virtue, are forc'd often to have recourſe to, ſeriouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting to their own Minds, thoſe future Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſes which the Goſpel aſſures them of, in order to the ſtrengthening their good Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54296:6"/>and the fortifying themſelves againſt the many Temptations they meet with in this evil World. By all which, we may perceive the great Uſefulneſs, and even Neceſſity of theſe Motives, which the Goſpel hath offer'd to our Conſideration. But this is not all; for</p>
            <p n="2">II. Our Bleſſed Saviour hath made farther Proviſion againſt the Indiſpoſition and Inabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Men, by promiſing the aſſiſtance of the Divine Spirit, for the enabling us to do what of our ſelves we cannot.</p>
            <p>Every created and finite Spirit muſt be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed neceſſarily and conſtantly to depend upon that Spirit which is uncreated and infinite, ever ſtanding in need of Influences from him. A ſtate of Innocency and Integrity cannot exempt a Creature from ſuch dependance. This,
<note place="margin">Lect. ij. p. 27, 28.</note> as I have formerly obſerv'd, reſults from the Nature and Condition of a Creature, to be of it ſelf muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and fallible, inſomuch that it can by no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther means preſerve its Integrity, than by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hering to its Maker, and deriving Influences from him. Much more then, upon the degeneracy of ſuch a Creature, ſome ſpecial influence from God muſt be neceſſary in order to its Reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very.</p>
            <p>It was, as I have taken Notice,
<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> from neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to adhere to God and depend upon him, that our firſt Parents apoſtatiz'd, whereby they and their Off-ſpring became, not mutable and fallible; <hi>that</hi> they were before; but, as Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience too plainly proves, very much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order'd
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54296:7"/>and weaken'd in all their Faculties, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving contracted an Indiſpoſition to that which is Good, together with ſtrong Habits of Sin. The Spirit, having once given way to the Fleſh, loſt its Authority and Government, which it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eaſily reaſſume.</p>
            <p>In order therefore to a recovery from this ſtate, to effect which is the great deſign of Chriſtianity, there muſt be a ſupply of new ſtrength, ſome extraordinary influences from the Divine Spirit, to reduce the Soul into good Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and to preſerve it, when ſo reduc'd. And for this we are beholden to the Undertaking of our great <hi>Mediator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true, good Men in all Ages of the World, ſuch I mean as have had a becoming ſenſe of God, and of natural Religion, have profeſs'd their reliance upon God, and there hopes of his aſſiſtance; and I queſtion not, but they have in ſome meaſure partaken of what they thus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for; which was in truth, though not clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtood by them, the effect of God's Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Grace through Jeſus Chriſt; whoſe Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, as we Chriſtians believe, had its effect for the benefit of Mankind, ever ſince the firſt Promiſe made to <hi>Adam</hi> after his Fall. But, as the greater part of Man were left to the ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions of Nature, and the conjectures of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in this caſe, having no expreſs Declaration or Promiſe, which they knew of, upon which they might depend; ſo the Pious and good Men amongſt the Jews themſelves, who enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Divine Oracles, yet believ'd and hop'd
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54296:7"/>for the aſſiſtance of the Divine Spirit, rather upon the grounds of natural Religion, than of their own Law, the Promiſes of which, as I before obſerv'd, were chiefly of the good things of this life, what was beyond this being rather obſcurely hinted to them, than plainly expreſs'd. For which reaſon St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who very well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the Jewiſh Law, and was thoroughly acquainted with the ſenſe in which his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen generally underſtood it, ſays,
<note place="margin">Rom. 7, 8, 10.</note> That <hi>ſin taking occaſion by the Commandment, wrought all manner of Concupiſcence;</hi> and again, That <hi>the Commandment, which was ordain'd unto Life, was found to be unto Death;</hi> and again, That <hi>the Law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">ch. 8.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>in that it was weak through the Fleſh, could not</hi> effect that <hi>Righteouſneſs in us,</hi> which it aimed at. By all which he plainly aſſerts, that the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> as ſuch, only declared Mens Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but brought no aſſiſtance along with it to enable them to perform it; and conſequently, left them in a worſe ſtate, than it found them, without the addition of Goſpel Grace.</p>
            <p>The Prophets indeed utter'd many Predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a plentiful Effuſion of the Divine Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit:
<note place="margin">Iſ. 44.3. Ezek. 36.26, 27. Joel 2.28.</note> But this was to be in the Days of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> as the Jews did, and we Chriſtians now do underſtand thoſe Prophecies to import. And they were accordingly fulfilled in the days of our Bleſſed Saviour; there having been a very plentiful Effuſion of the Divine Spirit upon the Apoſtles, and firſt Preachers, and Profeſſors of Chriſtianity, to enable them to do extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Works, and to capacitate them to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54296:8"/>and undergo their Employments and their Sufferings: And not only ſo, but we have more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, both from our Lord and his Apoſtles, expreſs and clear Promiſes of the Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſame Spirit, to enlighten and aſſiſt the Minds of Chriſtians in every ſucceeding Age.</p>
            <p>Our Lord to this purpoſe did in general de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the readineſs of Almighty God, <hi>to give his Holy Spirit</hi> to all thoſe who ſhould <hi>ask it of him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 11.13.</note> arguing from the goodneſs of God, and his fatherly care of Men, infinitely exceeding that of any earthly Parent.</p>
            <p>More particularly, our Lord hath given a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the Divine Spirit, to all ſuch as ſhall come to him, and believe in him. At a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Feſtival of the Jews,
<note place="margin">John 7.37, 38, 39.</note> 
               <hi>Jeſus ſtood and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſaying, If any Man thirſt, let him come unto me and drink. He that believeth on me, as the Scripture hath ſaid, Out of his belly ſhall flow Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of living Water.</hi> And <hi>this,</hi> as the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts adds, <hi>He ſpake of the Spirit, which they that believe on him ſhould receive: For the Holy Ghoſt was not yet given,</hi> (not in that plentiful man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as afterwards,) <hi>becauſe that Jeſus was not yet Glorified.</hi> And indeed it was after the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> that this Spirit was given, firſt in ſo wonderful a manner, as on the day of Pentecoſt, as a pledge of his being thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward to direct and aſſiſt the Church of Chriſt in all ſucceeding Ages, a Promiſe to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe being given to all the Members of the Chriſtian Body. For ſo St. <hi>Peter,</hi> diſcourſing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54296:8"/>to the Jews upon that occaſion,
<note place="margin">Acts 2.38, 39.</note> ſolemnly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares. <hi>Repent,</hi> ſays he, <hi>and be Baptiz'd every one of you, in the Name of Jeſus Chriſt, for the remiſſion of Sins; and ye ſhall receive the Gift of the Holy Ghoſt. For the Promiſe is unto you, and to your Children, and to all that are afar off, even as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as the Lord our God ſhall call.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis upon this account, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> declares ſo amply the Power which Chriſtians receiv'd by the Goſpel, to enable them to do what, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the Abilities of Nature, nor by the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> they could have done. When, in the place before-cited, he had complain'd of <hi>the Law in the Members</hi> whereby Men are <hi>Captivated,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7.23, 24.</note> and thereupon expreſs'd ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pathetically his Senſe of the <hi>Wretchedneſs</hi> of Men, by reaſon of <hi>the Body of Death</hi> which they carry about with them, he concludes with tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphing in the Grace of the Goſpel,
<note place="margin">v. 25.</note> 
               <hi>I thank God, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord;</hi> farther ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining himſelf in the following Words;
<note place="margin">ch. 8.1, 2, 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>There is therefore now no Condemnation to them which are in Chriſt Jeſus, who walk not after the Fleſh, but after the Spirit. For the Law of the Spirit of Life in Chriſt Jeſus hath made me free from the Law of Sin and Death. For what the Law could not do, in that it was weak through the Fleſh, God ſending his own Son in the likeneſs of ſinful Fleſh, and</hi> as a Sacrifice <hi>for Sin, condemned Sin in the Fleſh; that the Righteouſneſs of the Law might be fulfilled in us, who walk not after the Fleſh, but after the Spirit;</hi> as much as to ſay, that by embracing the Goſpel of Chriſt, he was not
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54296:9"/>only freed from <hi>Condemnation,</hi> on account either of his paſt Faults, or his preſent unavoidable Infirmities; but moreover received ſtrength through the aſſiſtance of the Spirit of Chriſt, which would enable him ſincerely, though not without all imperſection, to obey the Laws of God, and to attain to that <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> which through the inordinacy of the Fleſh, and the weakneſs of the <hi>Moſaical</hi> Inſtitution, he could not attain to before.</p>
            <p>For the ſame reaſon elſewhere comparing the Law with the Goſpel, he gives the preference to the latter, in very ſignificant terms. The <hi>Law</hi> he ſtiles <hi>the Miniſtration of the Letter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.3, 6, 7, 8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>which killeth;</hi> the <hi>Goſpel, the Miniſtration of the Spirit, which giveth Life:</hi> One, <hi>the Miniſtration of Death,</hi> and <hi>of Condemnation, written and engraven in Stone;</hi> the other, <hi>the Miniſtration of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, written in fleſhly Tables of the Heart, with the Spirit of the living God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But 'tis needleſs to recite more Paſſages, the New Teſtament is full of them; this being the great Promiſe of the Goſpel, declar'd through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Sacred Writings, that the Divine Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſhould be imparted in a free and plentiful manner to thoſe, who ſhould embrace the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>And this certainly is a ſufficient Proviſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the indiſpoſition and inability of Men's Minds to comply with the Divine Will, when reveal'd to them.
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.12, 14.</note> 
               <hi>The Law</hi> of God, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> expreſſes it, <hi>is Holy, and the Commandment Holy. Juſt and Good;</hi> the Precepts of the Goſpel are
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54296:9"/>
               <hi>Spiritual,</hi> and Divine; whereas we are <hi>Carnal and ſold under Sin:</hi> But the Spirit of God can reſcue us from this Slavery, by enlightning our Minds, fixing our Thoughts, inclining our Hearts, and ſpiritualizing our Affections, making us not only <hi>to delight in the Law of God after the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Man;</hi> but <hi>to walk</hi> alſo <hi>not after the Fleſh, but after the Spirit.</hi> The Example of our Lord was exact, and altogether perfect, and we muſt not hope in this life to attain to the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actneſs and perfection: But as it was upon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of its Perfection fit to be propos'd to our imitation; ſo the ſame Spirit which dwelt in our Lord, without meaſure, can form us by degrees after his likeneſs, and make us in our meaſure to reſemble him both in our Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers and Practices.</p>
            <p>If it be objected, that we want inſtances amongſt the Profeſſors of Chriſtianity, to verify this Doctrine, that the Divine Spirit is thus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted by the Goſpel; the Anſwer is eaſy. The primitive times of Chriſtianity abounded with inſtances of this kind. Such were the Apoſtles, who could every one of them have ſaid, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> did, <hi>Be ye followers of me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.2.</note> 
               <hi>even as I alſo am of Christ.</hi> And ſuch were abundance of the Members of the Chriſtian Body, which liv'd in and near thoſe times. Nay ſuch, thanks be to God, even ſince the degeneracy of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church, there have been and are to be met with in every Age; though, God knows, too few, to the great ſcandal of Unbelievers, who are not willing to conſider this matter tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:54296:10"/>but are forward to catch at any ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing advantage, for juſtifying their Inſidelity. In a word, we might all of us be inſtances of this kind, to the honour of our Lord, and to the credit of our Holy Profeſſion, if we would diligently uſe the means appointed for the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining this Divine Spirit, and faithfully im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove all his kindly motions upon our Minds; which brings me to the next particular I nam'd, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. That our Bleſſed Saviour hath made far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Proviſion in this Caſe, by ſettling ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions to be conſtantly obſerv'd and us'd in his Church, as are both in their own Nature proper to excite us, and are moreover deſign'd as Means of conveying the Grace of the Holy Spirit to us.</p>
            <p>The excellency of the <hi>Precepts</hi> and <hi>Example</hi> of our Lord will not engage us to Obedience and Imitation, unleſs we have them much in our view: The powerful <hi>Motives</hi> of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel will not affect us, unleſs they be ſeriouſly and frequently conſider'd by us: And the <hi>Grace</hi> of the Divine Spirit it ſelf, though freely offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet will prove ineffectual, unleſs it be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and carefully entertain'd and improv'd. Now as the indiſpoſition of Mens minds is great, ſo experience teacheth, that either the Buſineſs, or the Pleaſures of Life are moreover apt to employ or divert them to that degree, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſome farther courſe be taken to turn the Stream of their Thoughts the right way, all that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54296:10"/>we have hitherto mention'd may be loſt upon them. Beſides that the Spirit of God being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible, and his influences, ſuitable to his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſecret and indiſcernible to ſenſual and worldly Men (which is the reaſon our Saviour aſſigns, why <hi>the World cannot receive him,</hi> viz.
<note place="margin">John 14.17.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe it ſeeth him not, neither knoweth him;</hi>) it may therefore be very fit, nay neceſſary for us, who are us'd ſo much to converſe with ſenſible Objects, to have ſome ſtated, external, and ſenſible Means, for the deriving his inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Grace to our Spirits. Our bleſſed Saviour therefore knowing this to be our Caſe, hath kindly and bountifully provided for us in this inſtance alſo.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe, he hath not only caus'd his Word to be Written by thoſe who Converſed with him, and were Commiſſion'd and Inſpir'd by him, which we may at all times have free recourſe to our ſelves; but he hath farthermore appointed certain Inſtitutions, to be conſtantly obſerv'd in his Church, and ſettled an Order of Men as his Miniſters, to ſee them obſerv'd, and to perform their part in the obſervance of them. Thus he order'd the Apoſtles and their Succeſſors in the work of the Miniſtry, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive into the number of his Diſciples, all ſuch as ſhould profeſs their Repentance and Faith in him, by the external Rite of waſhing them with Water, in the Name of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt, thereby liſting and enrolling them, as Servants of the Bleſſed Trinity, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging them by a ſolemn and publick Profeſſion to declare themſelves ſuch.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:54296:11"/>
            <p> He hath farther ordain'd, That all his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, thus initiated, ſhall not only perform acts of Chriſtian Devotion by themſelves, but more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over that they ſhall frequently meet together, to joyn in the more publick Worſhip of God through Jeſus Chriſt, and mutually to exhort and encourage each other; particularly, that on a certain Day, every Week, beſides other occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſional Aſſemblies, they ſhall meet in moſt ſolemn manner, to offer up the ſacrifice of Praiſe and Prayer to the great Father of all, in the Name of his only begotten Son; and that at the ſame time his Word ſhall be Read and Preach'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, in order to the improving their Underſtandings, and the awakening their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and the cauſing them to remember and conſider the great Truths which they profeſs to believe.</p>
            <p>He hath farther appointed, That in theſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Aſſemblies, they ſhall frequently comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morate the great Sacrifice which he made of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upon the Croſs, by partaking of that En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment which he hath aſſign'd them at his own Table, thereby not only profeſſing themſelves all Members of the ſame Body, but at the ſame time alſo repreſenting to God, to themſelves, and to one another, the infinite love of God to Sinners, through a <hi>Mediator,</hi> and ſolemnly engaging themſelves afreſh to continue the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now theſe Inſtitutions, howſoever they may be deſpiſed by the prophane, unthinking, or ſupercilious ſort of Infidels, whoſoever ſeriouſly
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:54296:11"/>conſiders them, cannot but ſee, that they have a natural and ſtrong tendency to engage the Thoughts, and awaken the Minds of thoſe that uſe them, and thereby to render both the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts,</hi> and the <hi>Example,</hi> and the <hi>Motives</hi> of the Goſpel uſeful to the ends for which they were deſign'd.</p>
            <p>And if we will yet farther look into the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of them, we ſhall find, that they are more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over appointed by our Lord, as means of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving and conveying the Grace of his Holy Spirit to our Souls.</p>
            <p>Thus,
<note place="margin">Matth. 28.19, 20.</note> when our Lord commiſſion'd his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles <hi>to make Diſciples out of all Nations, bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing them, and teaching them to obſerve all things whatſoever he had commanded them,</hi> he immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately ſubjoyns, <hi>And lo, I am with you always, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto the end of the World;</hi> which can im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port no leſs, than his aſſiſting and bleſſing them and their Succeſſors, in the faithful diſcharge of their Miniſtry. He elſe-where declares in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,
<note place="margin">Matth. 18.20.</note> that <hi>where two or three are gathered together in his Name, there is he in the midſt of them, viz.</hi> by the preſence and aſſiſtance of his Holy Spirit.</p>
            <p>As to the Sacrament of Baptiſm, St. <hi>Peter</hi> is very expreſs, in the place before cited, where exhorting his Hearers to <hi>Repent</hi> and <hi>be Baptized,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 2.38, 39.</note> he encourages them by propoſing the Benefits which they ſhould receive thereby, namely, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Sins,</hi> and <hi>the Gift of the Holy Ghoſt, the promiſe</hi> of which, he ſays, was not to that Generation only, but <hi>to their Children, and to all
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:54296:12"/>that were afar off, even as many as God ſhould call.</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 3.5.</note> For which reaſon our Saviour himſelf, in his diſcourſe with <hi>Nicodemus</hi> joyn'd together <hi>Regeneration by Water</hi> and <hi>by the Spirit;</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> ſpeaking of the ſame Rite, ſays, that Chriſtians were <hi>ſav'd,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 3.5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>according to the Mercy of God, by the laver of Regeneration, and the renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Holy Ghoſt, which was ſhed upon them abundantly, through Jeſus Chriſt our Saviour;</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying, that Baptiſm with Water was the way of entitling Chriſtians to that Divine Gift, and a means of conveying it to them.</p>
            <p>And ſo likewiſe as to the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper, it is intended not only to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit to Chriſtians the Elements of Bread and Wine in Memory of our Saviour's Paſſion;
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.16.</note> but according to St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Expreſſion, <hi>the Cup of Bleſſing,</hi> then <hi>bleſſed</hi> is <hi>the Communion of the Blood of Chriſt, the Bread</hi> then <hi>broken</hi> is <hi>the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Body of Chriſt,</hi> viz. a <hi>Communion</hi> or <hi>Participation</hi> of all the Benefits purchas'd by breaking the Body and ſhedding the Blood of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> of which a principal one is, the Grace of the Divine Spirit to ſtrengthen our Souls.</p>
            <p>To conclude this particular; The Goſpel is ſtyl'd,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.2.</note> as I before obſerv'd, <hi>the Law of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Life;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.6.</note> the Miniſters of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are ſaid to be <hi>Miniſters not of the Letter, but of the Spirit.</hi> When they perform the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of their Function, one is ſaid <hi>to Plant,</hi> and another <hi>to Water,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.5, 6.</note> whilſt <hi>God giveth the increaſe,</hi> viz. by the Operation of his Holy Spirit accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying theſe external Miniſtrations; and finally the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:54296:12"/>Church is ſaid to be <hi>the Temple of God,</hi> foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as <hi>the Spirit of God dwelleth amongst</hi> and <hi>in</hi> the Members of it; all which paſſages do e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently import, that the external Miniſtrations of Religion in the Chriſtian Church, are deſign'd as ſo many means of deriving the internal Grace of the good Spirit to thoſe who faithfully make uſe of them.</p>
            <p>And as to this, I may preſume that it will not be pretended that any other inſtitution of Religion hath afforded the like means. The Jews indeed abounded in external Ordinances; which they were commanded to obſerve, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets themſelves intimate, and the Apoſtles more fully aſſure us, not as good in themſelves, but as ſuited to their temper and preſent circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances; which to free and generous Minds were indeed unpleaſant and burdenſome. Nor were they attended with that Promiſe of internal Grace and Aſſiſtance, which is annexed to the Chriſtian Inſtitutions. For as the Author to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> at large Diſcourſes,
<note place="margin">Heb. 9.10.</note> The Jewiſh <hi>ſervice ſtood only in Meats and Drinks, and divers Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhings and carnal Ordinances, impos'd on them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the time of Reformation;</hi> all which were <hi>on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Examples and Shadows of heavenly things:</hi>
               <note place="margin">ch. 8.5.6.10.</note> But <hi>Jeſus hath obtain'd a more excellent Miniſtry, by how much alſo he is the Mediator of a better Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, which was eſtabliſh'd upon better Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> viz. ſuch as theſe, that <hi>God would put his Laws into their Mind, and write them in their Hearts; and that he would be to them a God, and they ſhould be to him a People.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:54296:13"/>
            <p> Every other Profeſſion of Religion had like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe its external Rites and Ordinances belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it; but I think I may fairly leave it to the Judgment of any ſerious Deiſt, whether the Chriſtian Inſtitutions already mentioned, are not much more rational, decent, eaſy, and every way better adapted to the ends for which they are deſign'd, than thoſe of any other Religion, and conſequently, whether in this inſtance alſo our Bleſſed Saviour hath not made the beſt Proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for us.</p>
            <p>There remains yet one farther Difficulty which fallen Men lay under, which I am to conſider in the laſt place, and to ſhew that our Lord hath in that inſtance likewiſe made due Proviſion for us, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> An incapacity of removing thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther evil and miſchievous conſequences, to which their Sins had expos'd them; and of obtaining for themſelves that compleat Salvation which they ſtood in need of.</p>
            <p>The remaining Conſequences of our Apoſtacy from God, which I took notice of in a former Lecture,
<note place="margin">Lect. ij. p. 21, 22.</note> are all the Calamities of this preſent life, concluded at laſt with a Seperation of Soul and Body by Death, and followed in a future ſtate with all thoſe Evils, to which an immortal Soul ſeperated from its Body is there liable, which are more than we are able to enumerate, or ſo much as to conceive in the ſtate in which we now are.</p>
            <p>That Men were of themſelves altogether una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble either to avoid theſe Evils, or to deliver
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:54296:13"/>themſelves from them, is evident. No humane Wit or Power, as Experience proves, can ward off abundance of thoſe Calamities to which all Men are obnoxious from the preſent ſtate of things in this lower World; nor can the wealth of the richeſt Man upon Earth purchaſe an Exemption from them. The wiſe Man muſt die, as certainly as the Fool; the Prince, as the Peaſant; and the Rich Man, as the Beggar. Nor have any of theſe the leaſt power to diſpoſe of their Souls, when they are diſmis'd into the World of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits.</p>
            <p>Much leſs are they able to obtain for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that Salvation, which will compleat their Happineſs. All that is done for us in this life, even by our Bleſſed Saviour himſelf, is but the beginning of our Salvation; we are by him put into a ſttate of Salvation, and guided in the way which leads directly and ſurely to the completi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it: But we cannot be ſaid to <hi>be ſaved,</hi> till every evil diſpoſition be perfectly rooted out of our Souls; till our Spirits are reſtor'd to their perfect Health, and all the Habits of Piety and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue are confirm'd in them; nor indeed till our Bodies alſo ſhall be raiſed again and united to our Souls.</p>
            <p>For although the wiſeſt of Philoſophers, and the beſt of Chriſtians have juſtly complain'd of theſe Bodies of Fleſh, as clogs to their Spirits, and therefore may have deſir'd and choſen to be deliver'd from them, in order to have their Spirits ſet at liberty from their preſent incumbrance; yet the natural abhorrence which all Men have of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:54296:14"/>the ſeparation of their two eſſential parts made by Death, and that ardent deſire of life which is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted in humane Nature, ſeem plainly to inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, that we cannot be compleatly happy without conſiſting of Soul and Body united. And the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel conſirms this Notion to us, by cauſing us to wait for our compleat Salvation till the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Body.
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.19, 20, 21, 22, 23.</note> Thus St. <hi>Paul,</hi> having mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>the earneſt expectation</hi> which <hi>the whole Creation</hi> hath of <hi>being deliver'd</hi> from <hi>Vanity,</hi> and that <hi>bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of Corruption</hi> to which it is at preſent <hi>ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted,</hi> he adds, <hi>And not only they, but our ſelves alſo, which have the firſt fruits of the Spirit, even we our ſelves groan within our ſelves, waiting for the Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to wit, the Redemption of our Body.</hi> And to the ſame purpoſe again;
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.4.</note> 
               <hi>We that are in this Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle do groan, being burdened; not for that we would be uncloath'd; but cloath'd upon; that morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity might be ſwallow'd up of life;</hi> intimating, that Chriſtians will not be compleatly happy, till <hi>their Bodies</hi> ſhall be <hi>redeem'd</hi> from <hi>Corruption;</hi> and till their Souls ſhall be <hi>cloath'd</hi> with ſuch Bodies as ſhall be prepar'd for them at the Reſurrection; till which time, they will not be deliver'd from all the effects of the Divine Diſpleaſure, nor clearly <hi>manifeſted</hi> to be <hi>the Children of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now 'tis apparent, paſt all diſpute, that we can do nothing of all this for our ſelves; and that no other Inſtitution of Religion, beſides the <hi>Christian,</hi> hath diſcover'd to us, how it ſhall be done for us.</p>
            <p>But in this inſtance alſo, our Bleſſed Saviour hath made abundant Proviſion. The Goſpel hath aſſur'd us, and we Chriſtians do firmly believe,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:54296:14"/>as fundamental Articles of our Faith, that as our Lord died to made Expiation for our Sins, ſo he roſe again from the dead; and that then, according to his own Declaration,
<note place="margin">Matth. 28.18.</note> 
               <hi>All power</hi> was <hi>given unto him in Heaven and in Earth;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 1.20, 21, 22.</note> that <hi>God, having rais'd him from the dead, hath ſet him at his own right hand in the heavenly places, far a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all Principality and Power, and Might and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, and every Name that is named, not only in this World, but alſo in that which is to come; and hath put all things under his feet; and given him to be the Head over all things to the Church:</hi> as alſo, that he will according to his Promiſe come again to perfect the great Work which he hath under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, and which he hath been carrying on by all the Methods I have hitherto mention'd.</p>
            <p>Now allowing all this to be true, we have a plain account, how we ſhall be deliver'd from all the remaining evil Conſequences of our Fall, and be made perfectly happy, to the utmoſt of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and capacities.</p>
            <p>For hereby we are aſſur'd, That we have now a powerful Friend in Heaven in our own Nature;
<note place="margin">Heb. 4. 15, 16</note> One who <hi>can be touch'd with a feeling of our Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities,</hi> having been <hi>in all points tempted like as we are;</hi> and One who hath ſuch an Intereſt in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all, that by him we may <hi>go freely to the throne of Grace, obtaining Mercy and finding Grace to help in time of need:</hi> who although he doth not think fit to deliver us at preſent from all the Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of this Life,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.28.</note> yet will cauſe <hi>all things to work together for our good;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.13.</note> 
               <hi>not ſuffering us to be tempted above that we are able, but with the temptation alſo,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:54296:15"/>making a way to eſcape, that we may be able to bear it;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.9.</note> affording us ſuch a Meaſure of <hi>his Grace,</hi> as ſhall be <hi>ſufficient for us,</hi> and cauſing <hi>his ſtrength</hi> to be <hi>made perfect in our weakneſs:</hi> Who, although he permits us to remain liable to Death, as the juſt Reward of our Tranſgreſſion,
<note place="margin">Rom. 14.9.</note> yet being <hi>Lord both of the Dead and the Living,</hi> will receive our Souls at the hour of Death, and take care of them during their ſtate of Seperation, reviving them with his Inſluences, and filling them with the comfortable Expectation of their more compleat Happineſs. Finally we are aſſur'd, that as he will obtain of the Father, and confer upon his faithful Servants, all that is truly good and fit for them, during this ſtate of their Tryal, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their Spirits which they have committed to his Cuſtody, till his ſecond Appearance; ſo that he will come again in Perſon, redeem their dead Bodies, and perfect their Souls, reuniting them, and fully inſtating them in the favour of God, and beſtowing upon them the Inheritance of Children; of all which he hath given them at preſent <hi>his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> as the ſure <hi>Pledge</hi> and <hi>Earneſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is that Proviſion, which our Bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, according to the Declaration of his Goſpel, hath graciouſly made, in this laſt inſtance of our Neceſſity; after which I need add no more, this being the completion of our Felicity, and of our <hi>Mediator's</hi> Undertaking.</p>
            <p>And thus I have finiſh'd what I at firſt propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, with reſpect to the <hi>intrinſick</hi> Evidence of Chriſtianity, ſhewing its <hi>Credibility</hi> from conſidering the <hi>Perſons</hi> whom <hi>Chriſt Jeſus came to ſave;</hi> the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:54296:15"/>Nature of the <hi>Salvation</hi> which he propoſeth; and the <hi>Method</hi> in which he hath procur'd it.</p>
            <p>If in doing this, I have laid down <hi>a true Scheme</hi> of our holy Profeſſion (as I am verily perſuaded I have) according to the Doctrine of the Holy Scriptures, and the general ſenſe of the Chriſtian Church; and if through this whole <hi>Scheme</hi> there is nothing but what is highly worthy of God, and extremely beneficial to his Creatures; nay if ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Repreſentation of Chriſtianity, it not only infinitely excels all other Inſtitutions of Religion, but is ſuch, as that we are not able to frame an Idea of any Inſtitution comparable to it, (as I firmly believe upon impartial conſideration it will appear to be) it muſt then be granted that <hi>This is a faithful ſaying, and worthy of all acceptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that Chriſt Jeſus came into the World, to ſave Sinners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This therefore I heartily offer to the ſerious thoughts of all ſuch Men, as have a juſt ſenſe of <hi>God</hi> and of <hi>natural Religion</hi> upon their Minds, and have accuſtom'd themſelves <hi>to think ſeriouſly</hi> of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of importance.</p>
            <p>The <hi>external</hi> atteſtation, which God hath given to the Goſpel, by <hi>Prophecies, Miracles,</hi> and an won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful <hi>Succeſs</hi> in its Propagation, will tend, where duly obſerv'd, not only farther to confirm this <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſick</hi> Evidence, but alſo to awaken and excite the minds of thoſe, who are not us'd to ſerious think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; or are ſtrongly prejudic'd againſt Religion in general, through the violence of their corrupt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations. But when all is done, here we muſt fix; being aſſur'd, that as no Revelation can be
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:54296:16"/>from God, which is not worthy of him; ſo what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is ſo highly worthy of God as the Chriſtian Revelation is, muſt be <hi>credible</hi> upon its <hi>own account.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>May we, who profeſs to believe the Goſpel, both on account of its <hi>intrinſick</hi> Evidence, and the <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal</hi> atteſtation it hath had, and to be ſenſible of the excellent <hi>Method</hi> therein propos'd for <hi>the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Sinners,</hi> prove to the World the reality and the ſtedfaſtneſs of this our Faith, by its influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon our Spirits and our Lives. Then ſhall we our ſelves yield a farther atteſtation to the truth of our Bleſſed Saviour's Religion, by demonſtrat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing its Virtue and its Excellency to the unbeliev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And may Almighty God, who hath thus graciouſly revea'ld himſelf to Mankind, by his Son Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, ſend forth his holy Spirit, to accompany the preaching of this his Goſpel, ſo that it may be more univerſally receiv'd, and more thoroughly obey'd in all the Nations of the Earth, to the Glory of his Holy Name, and the Salvation of Sinners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now to the One God and Father of all, and to our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the only begotten Son of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with the Eternal Spirit; our great Creator, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, and Sanctifier, be aſcribed, as is moſt due, all Honor, Praiſe, and Glory, ſorever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:54296:16"/>
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>THE Author of theſe Lectures, having in the <hi>Second</hi> of them taken notice of an Objection, which he has not been able to conſider, within the compaſs of theſe <hi>Eight</hi> Diſcourſes, without interrupting the Order which he had propos'd to himſelf, deſigns, God willing, to publiſh a <hi>Ninth</hi> by way of Appendix to theſe, as a reply to the ſaid Objection.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
